<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Good nevves for the King of Bohemia? or, A certaine relation of the last and great ouerthrow, giuen by the Duke of Brunswicke to the Bishop of Cullen, and Duke of Bauariaes forces wherein was rumored, that Brunswicke was slaine. With the proceedings of Count Mansfield, since his last comming into the Palatinate, and since the Emperours ambassadour came into England, with other accidents, both in the Palatinate, and else-where. Sent of purpose by a person of account the eight day of April, and now published the seuenteenth 1622.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B14984</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.40</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102632</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838404</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838404</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177449</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B14984)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177449)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1379:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Good nevves for the King of Bohemia? or, A certaine relation of the last and great ouerthrow, giuen by the Duke of Brunswicke to the Bishop of Cullen, and Duke of Bauariaes forces wherein was rumored, that Brunswicke was slaine. With the proceedings of Count Mansfield, since his last comming into the Palatinate, and since the Emperours ambassadour came into England, with other accidents, both in the Palatinate, and else-where. Sent of purpose by a person of account the eight day of April, and now published the seuenteenth 1622.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 26 [i.e. 28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Bernard Alsop],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>P. 28 misnumbered 26.</note>
                  <note>Variant 1: title page has a colon instead of a question mark after "Bohemia". Variant 2: p. 28 correctly numbered.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 11354 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mansfeld, Peter Ernst, --  Graf von, 1580-1626.</term>
               <term>Thirty Years' War, 1618-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177449:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177449:1"/>
            <p>GOOD NEWES FOR THE KING OF BOHEMIA?</p>
            <p>OR; A Certaine Relation of the laſt and great Ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, <hi>giuen by the Duke of</hi> Brunſwicke <hi>to the Biſhop of</hi> Cullen, <hi>and Duke of</hi> Bauariaes <hi>Forces; wherein</hi> was rumored, that <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> was ſlaine.</p>
            <p>With <hi>The Proceedings of Count</hi> Mansfield, <hi>ſince his laſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into the</hi> Palatinate, <hi>and ſince the Emperours Ambaſſadour came into</hi> England, <hi>with other Accidents, both in the</hi> Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate, <hi>and elſe-where.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sent of purpoſe by a perſon of account the eight day of Aprill, and now publiſhed the ſeuenteenth 1622.</p>
            <p>Printed. 1622.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:177449:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177449:2"/>
            <head>A RELATION of the Duke of <hi>Brunſwickes</hi> and <hi>Mansfields</hi> proceedings againſt the enemies Forces in the <hi>Palatinate.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentle Reader;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ecauſe I ſee, that the generall <hi>Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantos</hi> coming weekely ouer, haue rather ſtifled their owne credites, then giuen ſatisfaction vnto the world; and that yet men throng as faſt to heare Newes, as they beyond the Seas throng ouer, and huddle together all manner of things to pleaſe the people, both here and elſe-where; I could not chuſe but take pitty of their longings and deſires, that are truly affectionate to Religion, and the Cauſe of the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and ſo expoſe vnto thee, whoſoeuer thou art, this Relation of credite, which came to my hands the twelfth of Aprill, wherein you ſhall ſee a modeſt declaration of the affaires of <hi>Germany,</hi> and the tumultuous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of ſuch <hi>Princes,</hi> as either wiſh well to the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> or ſuppoſe themſelues wronged by the Emperours imperiouſneſſe, and <hi>Bauariaes</hi> ambitious haſtineſſe to vſurpe anothers inheritance, and ſo I fall to the matter, as I finde it thus written.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:177449:3"/>
            <p>I will not trouble you, my ſelfe, nor contrarious humors; yea ſuch poore Papiſticall Newes-mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, that will haue <hi>Sluce</hi> loſt, and <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> ſlaine before euer they were in danger, with former repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions of matters already publiſhed, nor once diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute of the motiues, cauſes, effects, alterations, or any other circumſtances of the warres, eyther in <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia,</hi> or the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> but come roundly to the preſent buſineſſe, and tell you what is now a doing, and what is likely to follow.</p>
            <p>Euer ſince the Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> beganne to repine at <hi>Bauariaes</hi> intruſion into the honour of theſe acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the Emperour ſeemed partially affected to his ſeruice, many Princes miſliked the ſame, and by way of commiſeration thought it too much, that the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> ſhould be vtterly ouerthrowne; and therefore, as you haue participated out of diuers Diſcourſes, they haue recollected themſelues, and thus proceeded toward his reliefe and ſupportation: whereas it hath beene firſt generally reported, that <hi>Hungaria</hi> is reduced to the Emperours iuriſdiction, and that a League of Amitie hath beene contracted betweene him, and <hi>Bethelem Gabor;</hi> there is no ſuch matter, but rather the contrary. For the Prince of <hi>Tranſiluania</hi> calling the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> Goſſip, by reaſon he had chriſtned him a childe; hath proteſted neuer to forſake him, till he ſee him one way or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other re-eſtabliſhed: Indeed I muſt confeſſe he hath abſtained from crowning himſelfe king of <hi>Hungarie,</hi> vpon a certaine vow, he would neuer be inueſted, till the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> garriſons and Emperors forces were put out of Rub, <hi>Camora</hi> &amp; other places: yea till <hi>Preſhurgh</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:177449:3"/>it ſelfe were taken and cleered.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Marqueſſe of <hi>Ieggendorff</hi> keeping the fields and villages of <hi>Morauia</hi> for the vſe of the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> cleane contrary to the feare and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe he hath bene put in by the Emperours forces, hath giuen him ſeuerall defeates, and approoued himſelfe a faithfull friend and ſeruitor.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the repinings of <hi>Prague,</hi> and ſome other townes, which are ſtill vnder the King of <hi>Bohemiaes</hi> protection haue bene greater againſt the Emperour and his forces of late dayes, then euer before.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the Duke of <hi>Wittenberg,</hi> ſcarce named in other Relations, hauing muſtered ſome forces for the defence of his Countrey, and commaunded by the Emperour to vnite them to <hi>Bauaria,</hi> hath an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered plainely, That as they are muſtered by the aduice of his Counſell and Lords, they are likewiſe to be diſpoſed by them, who neuer had occaſion of vnkindnes with the <hi>Palatine,</hi> and therefore will not now beginne.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, the Princes of the Vnion perceiuing what a fearefull thing it is to let an enemy ſet footing in an others Countrey, eſpecially to fortifie himſelfe, as the <hi>Spaniard</hi> hath done in the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> are generall repiners at their owne firſt ſlackeneſſe, and ſo reſolue to recouer their much diſtreſſed honours by ſome new and glorious attempts in behalfe of their friend and confederate.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, the Marqueſſe of <hi>Boden,</hi> and <hi>Lantſgraue</hi> of <hi>Heſſe,</hi> ſtanding hitherto, as it were, at a ſtay, though they euer had good harts, wil now draw their friend together, and be ſeene in the field.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:177449:4"/>
            <p>Seuenthly, the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> comming but firſt into the Low countries, to ſalute the Queene of <hi>Bohemia</hi> at the <hi>Hage,</hi> offered them his ſeruice, and was not onely accepted, but ſupplied with men and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney by the <hi>Sluces,</hi> and ſo went directly into <hi>Weſtpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> and by degrees like a ball of ſnow waxed bigger and bigger, &amp; increaſed his forces, ſo that he attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Dioces of <hi>Cullen,</hi> &amp; proceeded in many glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioue actions which you haue heard of, and which haue indeed made him renowned ouer the world.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> though ſome vnkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe at the firſt paſſed between the Prince of <hi>Anhalt,</hi> and him, and all for the loue of the King of <hi>Bohemia:</hi> hath yet proſpered ſo well, that he came round about the countries, &amp; performed ſuch actions of admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that there are few kingdomes of <hi>Europe,</hi> which haue not bin filled with the relations of his proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and euer memorable exploites, ſo that he hath reduced diuers Prouinces vnder his obedience, and now ſtands like a worke impregnable with a mighty army and moſt willing heart to ſet forward the king of <hi>Bohemiaes</hi> deſignes.</p>
            <p>Theſe things are in the general thus ſet downe to ſhew you the cauſe, why the Emperor without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie is weary of the warre, and ſuſpects that his friends wil neuer be able to withſtand ſo great forces &amp; men exaſperated euery where againſt him, not ſo much for his owne cauſe, and great ſpirit in main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining his honour &amp; renowne, as hearkening to the <hi>Sirens</hi> ſongs of the Ieſuites, who in trueth care ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for him, nor any Prince whatſoeuer, nor for the ſlaughter of the people, diſturbance of their gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:177449:4"/>deuaſtation of their countries, and vtter ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of their quietnes, but for their owne ends &amp; ſuperintendency euen ouer the Pope himſelf: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he hath wiſely foreſeene greater miſchiefes, &amp; ſo doth politikely goe about to preuent the ſame by ſending an Ambaſſador into <hi>England</hi> for pacification (if it may be) of theſe troubles; but of this no more, til Time produce a fairer birth, &amp; make knowne the ſucceſſe of that Embaſſie, with all other things de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending.</p>
            <p>I will now go forward to the buſineſſe in hand, which depends on the actions of the Duke of <hi>Brunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke,</hi> and Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> who haue beene in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent imployment, euen ſince the Emperors Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour went into <hi>England,</hi> and moſt wonderfully ſet forward the King of <hi>Bohemiaes</hi> affaires, ſo that as far as men may be confident of worldly computation, ther is great hope of recouery, &amp; turning of fortunes wheele, that he may be brought at laſt to the toppe, which hath ſo long beene kept with his head downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: ſo that to make the matter more perſpicuous, I muſt ſay with the Poet; <hi>arma viroſqne cuno,</hi> and tell you firſt, what the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> hath done, &amp; next, how Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> hath proceeded.</p>
            <p>Concerning <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> he hath long ſince bin in poſſeſſion of <hi>Patter-horne, Weſtphalia,</hi> and the Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke of <hi>Cullen,</hi> wherein his progreſſes haue had won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull ſucceſſe, as by the preuailing in many skirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes may appeare, ſo that the Biſhop of <hi>Cullen</hi> being the duke of <hi>Bauariaes</hi> brother, hath diuers times ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſed the Emperor and the reſt of his friends, what diſtreſſe he hath bene in, and is likely to endure, if he
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:177449:5"/>be not better releeued, whereupon many by <hi>Bauari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aes</hi> appoyntment haue come to his aſſiſtance, namely <hi>Monſieur Iilley, Gonzales;</hi> another Prince of <hi>Anhalt</hi> and the Gouernor of <hi>Gulick,</hi> all which haue ſundry times skirmiſhed with the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke,</hi> and as you haue heard in as ſundry Relations could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer boaſt of preuailing, no not of equality in their encounters, but departed ſtil with loſſe on their ſide, while theſe skirmiſhes had their ſeuerall paſſages; Newes came vnto him of the King of <hi>Bohemiaes</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture from the <hi>Hage</hi> ſecretly in the company of ſir <hi>Francis Netherſoll,</hi> and ſir <hi>Charles Morgane,</hi> two Engliſh Knights, and eight other: ſome tolde him, that all his tents, armour and prouiſion of the warre were ſhipped at <hi>Enchyſen</hi> to goe to <hi>Bream,</hi> or ſome other rendezuous nearer to himſelfe, and the places he meant to goe vnto; ſome diſcourſed of diuerſe men of warre which attended him, as though hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued for <hi>Denmarke,</hi> but others ſeemed to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the truth indeed, and aſſured him he was gone diſguiſed from <hi>Calis</hi> to <hi>Sedan,</hi> to viſite the old duke of <hi>Bolloigne,</hi> and there to acquaint Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> with his intent, and purpoſes, and receiue from him and ſir <hi>Horatio Vere,</hi> a true Certificate of the eſtate of the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and the army, and ſo either to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect a Conuoy to meete with Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> or march with the whole army into ſom other country.</p>
            <p>When the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> heard of this, he forthwith beſtirred himſelfe, and ſet his actions on their beſt feete, that hee might be ready to attend the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> whereſoeuer hee went; and thus he preuailed in many ſeuerall encounters tooke
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:177449:5"/>diuers priſoners, ranſackt <hi>Patterborne,</hi> and <hi>Weſtphalia,</hi> marched as farre as <hi>Sipſtate,</hi> ſackt 8 or 9 townes, bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered diuers caſtles and forts, and al ouer put the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts in a generall feare, eſpecially the Ieſuites, whom of all others he hated, and of whom hee was ſome way reuenged: for they will haue him thus to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed againſt them in two ſeuerall places.</p>
            <p>Firſt, while he was reſident in <hi>Munſterland,</hi> and had according to the chaunce of warre, and cuſtome of Souldiers, pillaged the Villages, and ſpoyled the Inhabitants, two ſeuerall Ieſuites ſpared for no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uectiues againſt him, but railed in their Sermons, &amp; in euery Pulpit where they preached, miſ-termed him worſe then a tyrant, bloud-ſucker, and traytor, thundering againſt him curſes and damnation; yea curſing all his partakers and enterpriſes, whereupon the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> thus exaſperated, proiected how to be reuenged, and yet would faine do it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſhedding of bloud; whereupon he ſent a meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger for them, whom they denied, and added <hi>Elias</hi> prayers for fire from heauen to conſume the <hi>Captains</hi> of fifty: then he ſent certaine troups to ſurpriſe them, who tooke them in a manner of an Ambuſcado, and brought them before him; whereupon hee that was moſt faulty, kneeled downe, and importuned him to pardon his offence, and ſaue his life: at which <hi>Brunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke</hi> ſmiled &amp; anſwered; that his life would do him no good, but he would make ſome ſport with him to cheere his hart: &amp; thus prouing inexorable, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded certaine officers to ſtrip him naked, &amp; drop him all ouer with pitch and tarre, keeping him ſtil by a warm fire, that it might be moiſt vpon him, &amp; then
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:177449:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:177449:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:177449:7"/>they rowled him among feathers, till he was all ouer like ſome ſtrange foule, or monſter of <hi>Affricke:</hi> then he had a halter put about his necke, and ſo was led round about the army: laſt of all, he was ſent to the Nunnery, where the dainty Laſſes had work enough to make him cleane, and picke off his feathers.</p>
            <p>Another time after the ſurpriſing of a towne, in which were two Ieſuites more wealthy, then all the religious Friers in the ſame; he ſent certaine Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers vnto them, to inuite them to a Banquet, who though they were vnwilling to come, yet they durſt not deny; and when they came, were ſo extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily well vſed, that they beganne with iollity to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend his entertainment, and thought themſelues ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, becauſe of outward <hi>Curteſies:</hi> at laſt the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> drank to them, and told them, that he was certified they had much money lying by them, which they put to no good vſes; therefore he would play the Banker for them, and put it out both more charitably and piouſly; and when they began to deny it, calling our Lady &amp; the Saints to witnes, that they were abuſed and ſlandred, he ſware a great oathe, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding withall, as he wiſht the K. of <hi>Bohemia</hi> to thriue: he would flea them naked, &amp; torture them with pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, if either they dallied with him, or tooke not a preſent courſe to ſatisfie him: whereupon ſeeing no remedy, they brought his Officers to their Cloiſters, and ſhewed their treaſure, which amounted vnto 100000. dollers, and this was the end of that buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: but be not deceiued in this Relation about precedencie of time, as though this were newly done.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177449:7"/>
            <p>For it was the beginning of March laſt, and might haue bin ranked with his other actions, but that I ſuppoſe it came not within the reaches of common fingers, or dayly Corantos, and ſo I proceed to his laſt buſineſſe and encounters, which made way to a falſe reports of his death. You haue many times heard that <hi>Cordua</hi> out of <hi>Cruſmacke,</hi> Generall of the army, which <hi>Spinola</hi> left in the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier Tilley</hi> from <hi>Bauaria,</hi> as he could be ſpared came to the aſſiſtance of the Biſhop of <hi>Collen</hi> Prince Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, and receiued certaine ouerthrowes from <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke,</hi> who ſent his trophies of his ſpoyles to the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> as a rembrance of his ſeruice vnto her, whereupon euer ſince they haue watcht opportunity to be reuenged, and the Biſhop hath muſtered new forces, hauing ſupportation from the gouernours of <hi>Gulicke, Weſſell</hi> with certaine <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonions</hi> and <hi>Wallons,</hi> who preſently vnited themſelues to his owne ſubiects and people, and ſo made another ſtrong army which by the end of March was ready to march vnder the command of the yonger brother of the houſe of <hi>Anholt,</hi> and here ſirnamed the Prince of <hi>Anholt:</hi> all theſe watched the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke,</hi> and reſolued by ſome encounter or other to reinte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grate their former credite and loſſes, and dayly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him in the fieldes of <hi>Munſter, Weſtphalia, Pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne,</hi> and other of the Biſhop of <hi>Cullens</hi> Dioceſſe, till at the laſt they found him neere the towne of <hi>Warebrough,</hi> where they reſolued to ſet vpon him: but yet they found him not ſo vnprouided, either as they conceiued, or wiſhed. For by the meanes of Duke <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Sonderbergh,</hi> vnckle to the king of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:177449:8"/>a 1000. horſe was newly come to him out of <hi>Eaſt-Freeſland</hi> and <hi>North-Holland,</hi> vnder the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Captain <hi>Iohn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>honſon</hi> of the <hi>Hage,</hi> with cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine other ſouldiers, who all prepared themſelues to fight with this new commer, the forenamd Prince of <hi>Anholt,</hi> who greedy of honour, and willing to rank himſelfe in the Catalogue of famous Captaines, came brauely vpon that battaile, wherein the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> was fronted, nor was this raſhly done, or as I may ſay in ſpleene and fury, but vpon great aduiſe and deliberation. For beſides the <hi>Carbines</hi> that charged moſt violently, the Battalion was flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with Musketeers, who powred their ſhot into <hi>Brunſwickes</hi> battailes, and had the fortune to kill ſome of his men. For this was done ſo brauely, that his troopes were driuen to recoyle, and vpon that ſtaggering many thought he was ſlaine: for his horſe was ſhot vnder him, and in that amaſe the people ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moured his death.</p>
            <p>This was a hard beginning, and put the ſouldiers in a ſhrewd feare: For a whole Cornet of horſe was ſhiuered, and <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> lay for the time vnder foot, but it laſted not long: for his youth and courage got the victory of aſtoniſhment, and vp he gets, and vp he mounts againe, firſt cauſing the Captaines to to fill vp the roome with a body of pikes, who kept the enemies horſe from comming too forward: then did he charge them with freſh horſe, and ere they could wheele about to bring their piſtols bulleted he put them all to rowt, and ſo was quittance with them for their firſt branery: but taking another bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of pikes, and finding the enemies Battalion ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:177449:8"/>thin of Musketeers, he ſet vpon them in ſuch a manner, that he powred into them at the leaſt three ſhot for one, and iuſt at the ſame time charged them to their very faces, and had a braue diſpatch, had not the ſecond time his horſe beene ſlaine vnder him, and his ſecond fall, made his owne companie let fall their pikes, whereby they were daunted, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained from further proſecution, whereas queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe elſe they had made an end of that battaile, and that batttaile had ſure determined this controuerſie.</p>
            <p>But vp hee gets againe, and vp hee mounts with courage and alacrity, and with that fury that hee ouerpreſſed his enemies, and gaue ſuch example and encouragement to his Captaines, and ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, that in all the good Diſcipline of a skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh) I cannot call it a battaile, becauſe the main battailes neuer came to fight) they ſeconded one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, that the ſhot kild three hundred, at three vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and the pikes trooped, as it were, to make the more haſt to reſcue their braue Generall, who thus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimated, ſet thoſe horſe on worke that were neereſt and when the enemy began to ſhake, he preſſed them ſo violently, that many fell vnder his ſword, and by computation, this skirmiſh continued foure long houres, and ſurely had continued longer, if a braue <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Captaine newly come out of <hi>Gulicke,</hi> had not brought vp certaine Hargubuſh on horſebacke, and vnlookt for powred many ſhots into the pikes, which were ready to mingle with the Colonenſes, and at appoynt to end the buſineſſe, whereat the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> enraged came ſo audaciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that a Bullet grazed on his ſhoulder, and the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:177449:9"/>winde of many Bullets made him fall once againe from his horſe, inſo much that a <hi>Wallon</hi> Captaine (as it was reported) ſtepped vnto him, ſuppoſing to take him priſoner, but as he was lame in body, his buſineſſe ſucceeded as lamely: for to preuent the miſchiefe, one <hi>Remigius</hi> a <hi>Dane</hi> oppoſed the lame Captaine, and in the ſight of the armies ſlue him outright, hauing thereby time to fetch vp <hi>Brunſwicks</hi> horſe, and comfort to ſee him a liue, and vnhurt.</p>
            <p>Thus is hee mounted the third time, and percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the skirmiſh continue in ſome equalitie though the enemy had had the greater loſſe hee cauſed cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine field peeces of aduantage to be brought vp to the ſide of an hill, and mounted them ſo neere, that they were effectuall to the vnframing of a whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of pikes, vpon whoſe diſ-vniting ſome freſh com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies came in and ſo played their parts, that well breathed horſe couragiouſly gaue a new aſſault, and being well ſeconded, all was as well ended: for here were ſlaine 5000. and 800. taken priſoners. Beſides, Prince <hi>Anholt</hi> Generall of the <hi>Bauarian</hi> forces, who was alſo taken priſoner by the worthy Commander the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke:</hi> and the Biſhop had notice of a greater ſlaughter, which made him ſomewhat ſad and afflicted, till vnderſtanding that <hi>Brunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke</hi> was ſhot, and had loſt foure hundred men, hee was then cheered againe, and a noble Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late and Prince of Germanie, imputed all to the chance of war, and to the decider of controuerſies: notwithſtanding this ſeeming ſhew of vndaunted
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:177449:9"/>courage, he ſuſpected leaſt the great Citie of <hi>Collen,</hi> would animate the Souldiers to ſpoile, and make their approaches neerer and neerer, ſo hee retires himſelfe to a ſtrong Caſtle of his owne, vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that the Biſhop of <hi>Spiers</hi> had remoued to <hi>Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> and reſolued to ſecure himſelfe within the ſtrength of the Caſtle of <hi>Thermonsteno,</hi> as for the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Monts:</hi> it was told him he had leaue of the Duke of <hi>Loraine,</hi> or if you had rather the King of <hi>France,</hi> to keepe his Court in <hi>Mets,</hi> a ſtrong forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Towne and frontier Citie, which in thoſe dayes held out againſt the Emperour, and is ſtill the bulwarke and fortreſſe of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and odly hold in <hi>Loraine</hi> to ſecure the Countrey.</p>
            <p>This is that, which is written of the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicks</hi> proceedings, but would I had time to write more: For he is a worthy Gentleman, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Souldier, their lackes but ſome yeares to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture his iudgement, and bring theſe good begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings to proſperous ends, of which there is no doubt. For commonly forwards Springs, if to bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and hard Froſts doe not nip the buds, are not onely comforts for the time, but preſagers of plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Harueſts: and thus much for <hi>Brunſwicks</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings; now to the reſt, but eſpecially Count <hi>Mansfield.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Concerning the Earle of <hi>Mansfield</hi> and his ſtrong Army, many remarkable things are written, which as briefly as I can I will ſuccinctly abreuiate into theſe heads. 1. Firſt, that vnderſtanding, that all the Catholick Biſhops were fled, hee gariſoned
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177449:10"/>moſt of Army in their ſtrong holds, and quartred them in the Villages, whereby as they ſay in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> they had Miniſtrels fare, meate, drinke, and money. 2. Secondly, that when he perceiued his Army to encreaſe, and now to be ſo ſtrong, that the Monarchs of <hi>Europe</hi> looke vpon him with repining eyes, as wondering to what purpoſe he taketh ſuch large ſteps ouer the Catholick Countries, he made a defence or Apologie, diuulging it in the French tongue, and deliuered the Poſt of <hi>England, Balam</hi> by name, one of them to carie ouer with him. 3. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that vnderſtanding of the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicks</hi> conflicts, hee writ Letters of gratification, and not onely applauded his actions, but requeſted a certificate from his owne hands, who returned an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, how he had preuailed in many skirmiſhes: burnt <hi>Weſterkotton, Erquetts, Amruth,</hi> one of the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecks, Ruden, Vberhagen,</hi> and the <hi>Dioſarts</hi> houſe of <hi>Werdell</hi> come from <hi>Lipſtat,</hi> wherein hee had like to haue beene betrayed with 25. Cornets of Horie, 6000. Foot, diuers Peeces of Ordnance, Fireworks, ſcaling Ladders, and many Pyoners: vpon a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne of importance out, he ſuddenly heard of the approach of the Biſhops forces, and ſo was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to ſtay and augment his Army, for a more fiercer encounter: and that he had taken ſome pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, and ſome Friers, who were ſo obſtinate, that they cryed out vpon nothing but treaſon and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion. 4. Fourthly, that while hee was at <hi>Germe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhem,</hi> and retired to many places with his maine Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, Sir <hi>Horace Vere</hi> writing for ſome ſupplies, hee
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:177449:10"/>ſent to <hi>Mainhem</hi> foure Regiments of foot, ſome money, and munition, beſides many ſuppliments of victuall, and other prouiſion, whereof the Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon there ſtood in great neede. For in truth thus it was with the Engliſh Generall at this time, all the forces hee had were partly ſecured in <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem, Franckendale,</hi> and <hi>Heidelberg,</hi> partly Gariſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Villages, and partly running vp and downe for ſorraging, and other prouiſion: ſo that euery day in one place or other, hee was troubled with the Bauarians, and Monſieurs <hi>Tillyes</hi> Alarums, whoſe Souldiers might wel be called the Regiment <hi>Voluntes:</hi> For they neuer lay long quiet in a place, but had many imployments, as <hi>Bauaria</hi> vnderſtood of the Enemies proceedings, and Emperours plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, whereupon ſuſpecting what they might doe vpon aduantage, he ſent to Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> and was ſupplied accordingly: For without contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie, he caſt vp his accounts in this manner. That my Lord <hi>Chicheſter</hi> was long a comming with ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply into the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> but leaue the care of that to the Maieſtie of <hi>England,</hi> &amp; that if the Spaniards and Bauarians ſhould be remoued by way of rendition of the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſition for a peace, yet God knowes what might happen ere the buſineſſe were fully eſtabliſhed, and the peace abſolutely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded vpon: wherefore to ſtrengthen himſelfe, and to be informed of the ſtate of all affaires, he writ to Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> as you haue heard, and had not onely ſupply, but Letters of comfort concerning his reſolution, to continue conſtant to the Prince
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:177449:11"/>his Maſter.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Fiftly, that as he had fortified <hi>Haggenaw,</hi> hee would come and beſiege <hi>Lodenburg,</hi> and ſo prepare if neede be againſt <hi>Oppenheim,</hi> all which hee meant to doe with the third part of his forces: For he was perſwaded if the worſt came, no further ſupply would enter into the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> either from the Spaniard or Emperour, conſidering it was vnfur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and that <hi>Gonzules</hi> lay quiet, as if he had had a charge to fight no more. Befides wants ſo encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that the Countrey was not able to ſuſtaine an Army on any ſide. For the Engliſh were hardly driuen, and hardly releeued. <hi>Gonzales</hi> had beene put to the triall of eating his horſes: Monſieur <hi>Til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> perplexed with hunger &amp; ſeuerall imployment, ſo that he had ſcarce 5000. men left, and they ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to ſickneſſe, and other encombrances. The Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarians in the ſame predicarment vexed with ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and cold, although the Emperour had hether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſent many helpes, and renewed their decayed Souldiers: and the Townes, though the riuers brought in prouiſion, becauſe the Country people were reaſonably payed, yet felt the ſcarcity: For victuals grew deere in the Market, and the Burgers were glad to keepe good order without ryot or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe: yea, in many places Officers were ſet, as ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peruiſours, that neither the rich engroſſed the Corne, Wine, nor meat, nor the poore ſhould be ſtarued for want of neceſſaries. Theſe things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, hee tooke the more care in comming for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and peſtring the Countrey with his forces to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:177449:11"/>no purpoſe, but in my conſcience made acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the King of <hi>Bohemias</hi> retiring, he prepared to ſpeake with him, and ſo to attend to bring their buſineſſe to ſome perfection, as God ſhall giue way vnto the ſame.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Sixthly, that ſeeing he had viſited <hi>Alſatia</hi> all this Winter, and was in a manner Maſter of <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paldus</hi> his Countrey, he would ſure keepe what hee had gotten, and therefore as the Spaniard had taught him, and led the way in the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> hee would fortifie the ſtrongeſt places, and when all failed, put the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> in many poſſeſſion of Prouinces for his owne <hi>Palatinate,</hi> if not ſet the Crowne of <hi>Prague</hi> more firmely on his head, then ouer it was before.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Seuenthly, that ſeeing his endeuours had put him in a manner in poſſeſſion of foure Imperiall Cities, namely, <hi>Haggenaw, Spires, Wormes,</hi> and <hi>Ments,</hi> and that hee had brought them to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burſement of what money he liſted, he ſaw no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to let ſlip ſuch opportunity, but either keepe them in awe by his Armies, or make vſe of their ſeuerall Countries, to recompence the King of <hi>Bohemiahs</hi> loſſes, vntill a better time approach of better booty, which no doubt was now breaking out with the day to ſhew, that the Sunne of glory was ready to come out of his Chamber, to diſpell and baniſh away the contagious vapours of former trouble and diſcomforts.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Eighthly, that when the Emperour, or Duke of <hi>Bauaria,</hi> for the Emperour, by the aduice
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:177449:12"/>of the Biſhop of <hi>Collen</hi> had ſent vnto him to know, by what authority or in whoſe name hee either rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or kept together ſuch an Army: hee anſwered plainely and reſolutely, in Gods name, and the Kings, meaning the King of <hi>Bohemia:</hi> whereupon to expreſſe himſelfe accordingly, he contriued this deuiſe for his Enſigne, or colours a radiant Sunne in an Azure field, diſpelling a many ſlender and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porous clouds into a corner: thus hee not onely iuſtifies his actions, and emboldneth his Souldiers, but payeth his Army, and hath an orderly Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer for their monethly entertainment, according to the preyes and ſpoiles they take: yea, to order his buſineſſe the better, he is now coyning thouſands of Rikes dollers with this deuice, an arme comming out of a cloud, holding a ſword poynant vpward, with a Ieſuites Cap pierc'd through: the Motto round about, <hi>Amicus dei omnibus ſuis inimicis inimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus.</hi> 9. Ninthly, that although many Friers and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Preachers vſed as many fearefull inuectiues againſt the Warre, the cauſes, the Authors, and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, ſhewing plainly, it was a curſe of God where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it lighted: yet did he giue way vnto the Sun, as if hee were willing to confeſſe as much, intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting by many of his ſpeeches, that the Emperour, though he had wrong done him firſt by the <hi>Proge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes:</hi> yet tooke a wrong courſe to inflict the King of <hi>Bohemians</hi> children, with the loſſe of their inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for their Fathers fault: as for their Father, many a Chriſtian heart did thinke it reuenge ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to haue <hi>Prague</hi> ſurrendred, and to ſee the <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:177449:12"/>diſappointed of the Kingdome, in which hee was crowned and inueſted: but ſtill to haue his Countrey deuaſted, the territories depopulated, the Cities terrified with Souldiers: the Vines ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, the Woods cut downe, the cattell caried away, and all things ſubiect to the robberies of Souldiers, was too grieuous a reuenge, and vnmeaſurable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting: yet this was not all neither. For beſides the bringing in of ſtrange Nations, and a ſtrange Religion to a religious Countrey, he had by way of donation, enfeoffed another with the ſame, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring, what eternall hate might grow hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter betweene theſe two families, when peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture all the power of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> nor the Empire ſhould not reconcile them, which things orderly conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with many other dangerous to be publiſhed in a triuiall or common diſcourſe, made his actions the more iuſtifiable, conſidering the proceedings were ſo terrible, and although the Ieſuites aymed at him in their Sermons, as the Author of thoſe fearefull effects, and prodigious calamities, which the beſt Warre muſt procure: yet all the world knowes the Spaniards were poſſeſſours of the one ſide, and <hi>Bauaria</hi> was entred in the other, before euer he ſet footing therein, or tooke this courſe of the Warres diuerſion, which by Gods grace and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, who ſet him on worke, hee would proſecute as long as life laſted, or the King of <hi>Bohemias</hi> buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hung in ſuſpence.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Tenthly, that ſeeing the Duke of <hi>Bauaria</hi> hath finiſhed the bridge ouer the Neckar, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:177449:13"/>diuers Wagons to come that way already with Corne and other prouiſion, and that Monſieur <hi>Til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> quartereth himſelfe neere <hi>Heidelberg,</hi> as though he meant to beſiege the ſame, or at leaſt tarry the time, till <hi>Bauarias</hi> forces be renewed, that ioyning together, they may performe their worke effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, whereby it is ſo giuen out in <hi>England,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are credulous of ſuch an impoſſibility: he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued to ſhew them no fauour, whereſoeuer hee come: but as hee hath viſited <hi>Laudenburg,</hi> and the ſtrong Caſtle of <hi>Magdenburg,</hi> belonging to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick of <hi>Spires,</hi> he will alſo come to <hi>Beſsing,</hi> and the Marqueſſe of <hi>Danſtarrats</hi> Countrey, who was euer an Enemy to the Princes of the Vnion: for feare whereof the people haue already vnfurniſht their fields of their Cattle, and caried their goods into the ſtrongeſt holds, at which Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> ſmiles to thinke, that poore Caſtles &amp; Forts ſhould ſecure them, when ſo many Cities and wel fortified places haue ſubmitted to his mercy, and made their attonement with him, yea the other day the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks about <hi>Spiers</hi> and <hi>Wormes,</hi> ſeeing the good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour of his Souldiers, that they neither raui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed women, nor murthered men, but onely tooke the pilledge of the Countrey, rifled the houſes, the common cuſtome, and faireſt courſe of a conquering Army, condiſcended, and by a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall conſent agreed to allow him 3000. mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Corne, 200. Fats of Wine, and 60000. Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines, which though he did not accept of, as a full ſatisfaction to his demaunds, yet did hee take in
<pb facs="tcp:177449:13"/>good part for the preſent, and knew that if neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhould occaſion, they would be drawne to a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther compoſition and disburſement.</p>
            <p>Thus for the time he deſiſted from vrging them to more then they were willng to graunt, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring he had formerly drawne great ſummes of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney out of their Treaſuries: whereupon he procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to viſite other Countries, and therein onely to take an oath of the Inhabitants of loyalty and fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and ſeruice and atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dancie to himſelfe, and ſo he paſſed to the other ſide of the <hi>Rhine</hi> into the Countries of <hi>Didiſhene</hi> and <hi>Anoth,</hi> where the people ſeemed to wiſh well vnto the King of Bohemia, and very willingly tooke their Oath: then paſſed hee to the Graue of Louenſteins Countrey, which lyeth within the Biſhopricke of Spires, and taking the ſame Oath of the inhabitants, he quietly receiued ſuch prouiſion and money, as they would willingly ſpare: heere hee receiued newes that Monſieur <hi>Tilly</hi> had brought his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, or Artillery to a place called Huſcharen, as if he meant to goe to Heidelbergh indeed, but he let him alone, as reſoluing, that though he had power to his will, yet hee ſhould not attempt any enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe of worth and moment, without interception: but aſſured, that neither Bauaria could proceed in any ſuch deſigne, nor durſt he lying ſo neare, but let them alone, till he had further directions from him, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he longs to ſpeake withall; ſo that in my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience when that oportunity ſhal preſent her hairy ſoretop vnto him, he will onely march through the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:177449:14"/>Palatinate into Bauaria's owne Countrey, and ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make him looke to a new buſines, or inrich his Army with the ſpoyle, that hee may be the better prouided to paſſe into Bohemia it ſelfe.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Eleauenthly, though he heard, that <hi>Don Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dua</hi> in perſon was riſen from the Towne of Cruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nach to goe to Openhem, and fortifie the Bridge with Sconces to hinder all paſſengers, but ſuch, whom the Court of Guard ſhall licenſe: yet when he ſaw he ſlacked the ſame, hee conceiued he had ſome ſpeciall charge to proceed no further againſt the Engliſh, till the Emperours Ambaſſador were returned, and they knew what to truſt vnto from <hi>England:</hi> So that one way hee found the people glad, that there was any glimmering light of Peace toward, and another way feared it would be a barre vnto his Deſignes, if the King of Bohemia ſhould by any meanes be ouer-ruled, or perſwaded to eaſie Condition, and tractates of Friendſhip: but reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued not to be diſturbed with conceit, or meditation of ſuch buſines, which yet hung in ſuſpence, or were Coniecturall, he preſently put himſelfe into Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ouerlooked his Fortifications and places, wherein he had Garriſon'd his Souldiers, and ſet vp his reſt to attend the good houre of further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Twelthly, it was ſomewhat vnpleaſing vnto him, that his Forces had layne ſo long before the Caſtle of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gdenburg,</hi> and ſpent as hee thought ſo much time to his diſgrace, and hindring his other deſignes, whereupon he went thither in perſon and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:177449:14"/>tooke away all meanes from them of ſuccor and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, which when they perceiued, and were now debarred from former ſupportation, being old Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers and of great experience, they came to capitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the matter, and ſurrendred the place vpon Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to ſaue their liues, and depart with Bag and baggage, which they did without Colours diſplay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or any ſhow of a Souldier; by which occaſion Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> tooke poſſeſſion of the ſame, and found therein more wealth, then either he had at Spiers or Wormes: Thus did he preuaile in his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and is now Lord of many Countries &amp; holds, attending the good houre of the King of Bohemia's comming to him, or ſending for him: and ſo leaue him to the glory and in the fulnes of ioy, for this laſt good ſucceſſe, which hath made him more confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent &amp; reſolute to ouerſway nicer exceptions, and goe forward in his pretences, though as yet he hath not fully expreſſed the ſame concerning particulars.</p>
            <p>Hauing thus left Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> in ſecurity, full of wealth, Glory, and aſſurance to bring his purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to a happy period. Let vs now come to other matters, not yet impertinent though not altogether depending vpon the former: You haue heard I am ſure by many relations publiſhed long ſince, that Duke <hi>Leopoldus</hi> Lord of Elſas and Alſatia, was in a manner driuen out of his Countrey by the Forces of <hi>Mansfield:</hi> yet prettily ſalued that wound with this cure, that he went into the Valtolina, as Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall for the King of Spaine, though in his hart he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pined at ſuch an Vſurpation, which was euer belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:177449:15"/>to the Gouernment of another Prince. For of late the Houſe of Auſtria condiſcended, that Spaine ſhould haue the prerogatiue, as hee had the Forces and ſtronger hand to holde them cloſe to his Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines and preuayling. Well? heere hee muſtered Soldiers and tooke vp two Regements to ſupply o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Armies, but in the midſt of this iollity, as hee was running away with hopes of recouery or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge: the money which was promiſed him out of Spaine fayled, and he could neither goe forward in that buſines, nor durſt returne into his owne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey for feare of greater forces, or more violent op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition: But ſome report, that the Emperour ſent him word, that hee was willing to a generall Peace and for that purpoſe had ſent Count <hi>Siratzenburg</hi> into England as his Ambaſſador, and therfore there needed no ſuch haſtines to giue any cauſe of ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that hee meant not ſincerely as he profeſſed: This treaty of Peace ſet all humors and diſpoſitions on worke, and the Prouinces were as it detayned between feare and gladnes, what would be the iſſue of the ſame, as for the <hi>Grizons</hi> &amp; <hi>Swiſſe?</hi> they ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Leopoldus</hi> a face of diſcontent euery way, and brought out olde Records, wherein the Kings of France were authentically ſworne to bee their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors, how euer now they ſlacked the ſame, and gaue way to anothers Greatnes, the like might be ſaid of the Palatinate, Cleue, and other bordering Prouinces vpon the Empire, and confines of Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy: but times are alterers of mens purpoſes, and Kingdomes are eaten out with contraries; &amp; taught
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:177449:15"/>to know a leſſon of Humiliation, when the Lord of all Kingdomes will admit of other Stewards, then he firſt placed: Thus <hi>Leopoldus</hi> muſt be content to ſee another man in poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of many of his Townes, and other Prouinces of the Biſhops, aſwell as the Palatinate was at the ſame inſtant vſurped by ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and had indeed too many Maſters.</p>
            <p>Amongſt other hopes and helpes, that the King of Bohemia hath, the Marqueſſe of <hi>Ieggendorffe</hi> is not the leaſt. For hee muſtreth Soldiers dayly both in Sileſia and Morauia, yea hath had ſupply out of Walachia: and at this houre is doubtfull, whether he ſhall entertaine the <hi>Tartars</hi> or no, who came both to him and <hi>Bethlem Gabor</hi> by thouſands, and reſolue to aſſiſt them, if need be againſt the Emperour, ſo that there is a great feare in Preſlaw and Gratz, Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Sileſia, what ſhall become of them, if any al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration happen: whereupon the Lords and States raiſe vp many Forces, fortifie their Citties, prouide men, money, and munition, ſtand at a ſtay for their ſubmiſſion, and doe neither openly warrant the Emperour their abſolute Obedience, nor priuately wiſh ill to the King of Bohemia's proceedings, with which kinde of neutrality the Emperor is ſo diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that he imputes the fault to the Duke of <hi>Saxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi> negligence, as vnderſtanding that many Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of Saxony, haue bin licenſed to depart home, and the Duke himſelfe is weary of the Warre; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding theſe proceedings, and that there is a reſtraint of the Soldiers fury and violent cuſtomes, whereby <hi>Prague</hi> and other places, reduced vnder the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:177449:16"/>Emperours gouernment, doe yet hope and looke after ſome order for their Religion, and profeſſion of a good conſcience: yet doth the Biſhop of <hi>Prague</hi> proceede moſt violently and cruelly againſt the Proteſtants, and will not ſuffer them to profeſſe publiquely either in Churches, or priuate houſes, any thing againſt the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſo that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where the Inhabitants or diſcontented, and pray to God for the diuerſion of theſe miſchiefes, that haue not onely dilacerated the peace of <hi>Europe,</hi> but broken the hearts of poore ſoules to heare God ſo prophaned, and euery man in his owne particular terrified. For how euer it is reported, that in <hi>Sile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, Luſatia,</hi> and thoſe Countries, there ſhall be a preſent aſſembly at <hi>Eaſter</hi> of the Lords and States of the Prouinces, yet hath the Biſhop of <hi>Newes</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the example of the great Biſhop of <hi>Prague,</hi> and locked vp the Churches from the Proteſtants, and will not ſuffer the Burgers to make open pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of their conſciences; whereupon by way of petition they haue ſollicited the Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> to conſider their poore eſtates, and how euer, the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour muſt captiuate their bodies and goods; yet to giue them leaue to haue their ſoules free to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow vpon the God of all freedome, and ſaluation: to which hee not onely anſwered very graciouſly, but gaue way vnder hand to all their Proteſtant aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, and religious meetings, ſo that there is hope and light appearing, that either the Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> is and will be diſcontented with the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, whereby the vehemencie of his proceedings
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:177449:16"/>may be ſlacked, or that hee will ſuffer the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants to enioy their owne freedomes, and peace of conſcience, to which purpoſe they haue procured another Mediator, euen Duke <hi>Weymar</hi> of <hi>Saxony</hi> his owne kinſman, who hath not onely profeſſed himſelfe a Proteſtant, but raiſed two thouſand foot, and fiue hundred horſe to ioyne with the Duke of <hi>Brunſwick</hi> in his proceedings, not doubting very ſhortly to be partakers of his glory, as well as of his ſpoiles, and hardly gotten conqueſts.</p>
            <p>Thus are the pure and delicate waters of Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropes peace troubled and bedirtied with the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton flingings of cruell handes: For Warre you ſee hath throwne Blood and corrupted Carkaſſes into the Sunne: men haue followed one another with Death and reuenge, and ſo drenched their ſtincking feete: Women haue bathed their rauiſhed bodies and left their pollution behinde them: Souldiers haue waſhed their corrupted woundes, and all ſorts with one filth or other, haue ſought to damme vp the ſtreames, and make the currant (if it were poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, vnpaſſible) ſo that vnleſſe the ſtirring waters get the vpper hand, all will be ſpoyled, and if it once come to a ſtanding poole, it will ſtinke and putrifie: but the ſame God, that ſent the Angell to quicken the poole of <hi>Shilo,</hi> that the diſeaſed might be cured, the lame reſtored, the dropſie healed, the leprous clenſed, &amp; all infection purged, wil when he ſees his time, performe the like for vs, by turning
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:177449:17"/>the inundation another way, and making the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers runne ſmoothly within their own euen bankes, or elſe he will doe, as he did by the waters of <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah,</hi> or by the flood <hi>Iordan,</hi> which was preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Springes <hi>Damaſius</hi> to heale <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Sirian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which purpoſe, let all thoſe, who wiſh the Peace of <hi>Syon,</hi> and the building vp of the walles of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> bring Incenſe and Sacrifice to the Altar of the Temple, and there lift vp their handes and hearts, that it may be propitious, and the God of Heauen not only ſcent a ſweet ſmelling ſauour: but giue vs notice of accepting our Prayers, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, by ſeeing the Angell aſcend in the flame.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
